[Music]
[Applause]
band glute burnouts you see them
everywhere they're all over the place on
social media
everyone's doing them this video is
dedicated to how to construct
a proper band burnout now one thing i'm
seeing is that a lot of trainers a lot
of
lifters a lot of fitness chicks out
there they're prescribing band burnouts
and it's all abduction movements it
might be like
six straight movements with a band on
all being abduction
that's not optimal because you need to
alternate between
abduction and extension hip extension
movements this way you're
not only are you targeting more regions
of the glutes but you're also
giving some areas some rest so that they
can recover they're not
constantly fatigued i've been doing
these for many years but my first
instagram post dedicated to these was on
december 17th of 2017.
this was with my client masa and i had
started to do these
with my clients like i would have them
put the band above their knees so they'd
put a glute loop above their knees
and then i would do do it with them and
they'd copy me
the thing is i didn't have a banner on
my knee so it was easy for me but what i
liked about it at the time was
the like camaraderie you built with your
client like you're doing it with them
it's fun
they loved it uh you know you wanna
if you if you want to gain clients as a
personal trainer you gotta go above and
beyond and by doing this i showed my
clients like i'm in this with you
let's have some fun you know they would
laugh it kind of looks like you're
dancing so i started doing it with my
client masa at the end of every workout
and i just call it a burnout
before i would do them as separate
workouts but i had a
friend named jim aaron he's in in oregon
he actually put me through a band
burnout
and he just wouldn't let me stop and i
did like three movements in a row
and the next two days my upper glutes
were very sore and i thought this has to
work like and it let me know i need to
i need to take these more seriously and
work harder at them because i'm probably
leaving some room in the tank in terms
of upper glute development you know
along the way they went from they start
off at two minutes and then i went to
three minutes as my clients got more
advanced so now i do three minute
burnouts but if you're a beginner i just
do two minutes so you start out at two
move to three and i don't keep
increasing i don't want him to get to
ten minute burnouts i don't think it
would be more effective that way now i
did write about these in
glute lab my book and i provided a
template as to how to set up a proper
band glute burnout
i've modified it just slightly since the
time the book was written
and today i'm going to present you with
that template so if you copy this system
you're sure to get a great glute workout
and it's an
optimal sequence for you and your
clients so again it's a three-minute
burnout and there's
five different categories so you're just
gonna select one movement from each of
the five categories and voila you've got
yourself a proper burnout
first up you're gonna select a frontal
plane hip abduction movement now
frontal plane means you're straight up
either standing straight up or you're
perfectly side lying
you're not bent over at the hips at all
and this works more the upper glutes so
you're going to do 30 seconds with that
then you're going to move on to a hip
extension movement
now these you're going to do for 60
seconds because you'll do 30 seconds
with one leg
30 seconds with the other leg and hip
extension works the entire glute after
that
you're gonna select a transverse plane
hip abduction movement so
transverse plane means you're bent
forward okay it still does
target the upper glutes but it brings
the lower glutes more into play and
again
you're folded over moving your legs in
and out and you're gonna do this for 30
seconds
so now we're at around the two minute
mark and you're gonna pick a type of
glute squeeze
you're gonna do this for 30 seconds and
you squeeze the glutes as hard as
possible this is going to improve
your ability to maximize tension on the
glutes and it'll transfer over to
dynamic exercises as well
and finally you're gonna finish off with
30 seconds of a combined
hip extension hip abduction movement now
these work the lower and upper glutes
but probably a little bit more the upper
than lower but after this your three
minute is up
and when the client finishes these you
can allow them to collapse on the floor
because their butts will be burning i
promise you that okay so i wanted you
guys to see what a band burnout looks
like
in real life so i've got grace with me
young grace
and uh we're gonna do a three minute
burnout i'll explain the exercises
briefly have her do a few reps then
we'll fast forward him i just want you
guys to see
what she looks like at the end of the
three minutes so i've got my style watch
and i'm gonna make sure
we go right to the three minutes okay
first exercise
for the frontal plane hip abduction is
the lateral band walk she's not gonna be
squatting with these she'll be upright
okay
ready go just left
left right longer strides
longer okay we're going 30 seconds here
okay we're at 10
20.
okay three more seconds
okay good now post up against here
all right we're doing a kickback 30
seconds on one leg
just like that straight back good
good
five four three
two one next side okay good
kick that back keep going boom
five four three two
one okay now we're gonna move over to
here you're gonna have a seat
right here have a seat
we're gonna go band seated hip abduction
all right hands on hips
just start nope let's pull this okay go
out out out roll to the latter edges of
your feet
good keep going fast
three four five get down on the ground
in a plank
this isn't really using the band get
down your elbows okay
right here yep now squeeze the glutes as
hard as you can post your tilt hold it
just like that
hold it hard squeeze as hard as you can
good
keep going keep going keep going yep
keep squeezing you'll feel this in your
glutes and you'll feel this in your abs
keep squeezing keep squeezing you can
see these turned on
by the way she's holding that it's just
a big glue squeeze
all right five four three
two one now lay on your back flip around
okay glute bridge okay
start by pushing the knees out as far as
you can hold it there bridge
go for it good two
four five hold this one for test second
one two
three four push out five six
seven eight push high nine ten
done
grace there is no swearing on my youtube
channel
i'm just kidding let me help you up
now this is perfect time to take a
picture
of the thumbnail is that what's called
thumbnail perfect time for the thumbnail
now that she's got a massive glute pump
now that actually lasted three minutes
and 30 seconds because
you know you take five to ten seconds
getting them into position for the new
exercise so you got to take that into
account
all right so now your three minutes is
up the client's glutes are burning like
crazy
you know you give them a high five you
give a hug come at a great session and
they're on their way the million dollar
question is do they work
i think it's very important as a
scientifically minded practitioner to be
skeptical of
even your own methods if you know a lot
about the physiology of muscle
hypertrophy then you could make a strong
case why these do work you know
you could say they provide additional
metabolic stress
they give you a pump that's cell
swelling you know
the the pump the burn the mind muscle
connection you're focusing
you're going to improve your nervous
system's ability to recruit the fibers
it's going to give you more muscular
endurance you're doing unique movements
that target different fibers but you
could
also use physiology to explain why they
won't work
kind of like aerobics you know you're
doing like a three-minute aerobic
routine
are you going heavy are you taking
anything to complete failure sure you're
burning the whole time but are you just
fatiguing your glutes and creating
unnecessary muscle damage and fatigue
where it's going to hamper the next
day's session self-swelling is
theoretical you know
my buddy brad schoenfeld i wrote a paper
on it but it's theoretical
is it swelling inside the muscle cell or
outside of it if it is inside the cell
is it enough to cause an adaptive
response does the ultrastructure of the
cell
perceive this to be a threat and it
ramps up protein synthesis
to create a stronger unit basically as
some trainers have eloquently put it you
might just be doing
around it so i don't know whether it
works well or not it might depend on
different factors but what i always say
in my seminars is i take the shotgun
approach i would love to have
a rifle and be able to hone in on what
works we just don't know enough about
muscle hypertrophy yet so i try to cover
all the possible bases
i know in 10 years i'll look at my
system and i'll say i was wrong there
was wrong there
but right now i do include them in my
protocols
and here's why firstly for the reasons i
just mentioned it could improve
hypertrophy through increased metabolic
stress
mind muscle connection pump burn second
buy-in you want your clients to be
pumped for their workouts you want to be
excited about the session and let me
tell you
the clients love this they love the
interaction between you and them
they feel like you're in the trenches
with them it's new it's fun
like i said it's kind of like dancing
together and they like finishers like
look at the popularity of like p90x and
crossfit people like to feel
punished at the end of the workout they
like feeling exhausted like they exerted
themselves maximally and this helps give
them a little bit of what they need and
third of all
you'll get texts on their drive home
sometimes i'll look at my phone
it's like ass still on fire booty still
burning 30 minutes later you know if
some stranger would have looked at my
phone they'd be like who the hell is
this guy
but i know it definitely improves client
buy-in and when they believe in the
program
it increases results i mean there are
studies showing the power of placebo
the power of expectation psychology
influences physiology
they're gonna go to sleep they're gonna
they're gonna wake up more excited about
their workout with you and i don't feel
like it can hurt that much as long as
you don't overdo it
so give these three minute band glute
workouts a try do them just how i
mentioned
you know select from the five different
categories totaling
180 seconds use your stopwatch and you
and or your clients glutes will be
better off as a result
if you like what you saw please be sure
to hit like leave a comment
and make sure you're subscribed my
channel i've got a lot more to come
hey guys thanks for watching till the
end i realized some of this info
was a little technical and complicated
so as a gift to you i created a little
pdf that you can download just click on
the description there's a link there
go ahead and download it and if you have
questions about the exercise
in time i'll try to post descriptions of
those
like the cha-cha i've posted it on
instagram but never on youtube
just give me some time it'll all make
sense thanks for watching i hope you
find it to be beneficial
now if this video intrigued you and you
would like to train
under my system using my principles then
i invite you to click on the link below
and subscribe to booty by brett and join
the thousands of other happy members
who are seeing amazing results
you